INSTRUCTOR: Hey everyone,
welcome to our first week
in Excel.
We are going to
dive straight in.
And whether you are
already an Excel user
or if this is your first time
opening up the application,
welcome.
This course is really
designed to help
you either get that additional
practice or get your feet wet.
Our goal is to give
you the foundations
that you can continue to build
through your other coursework
and in your professional
careers the set of Excel skills
that are tailored
to your career path.
These are just the foundations.
I've been using Excel
for over 10 years,
and I'm still learning
tips and tricks
every time I open it up and am
confronted with a new problem.
So I want to give
you the confidence
to be able to answer data
questions in a tool like Excel,
when Excel makes sense to
answer those questions.
So today, what we're
going to really focus on
is understanding Excel--
really get to know our way
around the application.
And then we're going to answer
some of those data questions
that we can answer with
summary statistics,
sorting and filtering,
and understand really
how can we start
to manipulate data.
And again, data is just
information that we collect.
Data comes from everywhere.
It's all over the place.
Businesses want
more and more data.
And what we're able to
do then is take the data
and use it to inform
future decisions.
And that's the beauty
of data analysis.
Whether you have an analyst in
your title in the future or not,
you're going to be
taking this information
and making decisions.
You do this every day,
whether you realize it or not.
You open your weather app, and
you see that it's going to rain.
That's data we've collected.
We're pretty sure
it's going to rain.
We don't actually know if
it's going to rain or not.
Our models are pretty good, so
we've got a really good idea.
You take that information
into your own personal life
and you're like,
oh, I need to bring
a rain jacket or an umbrella.
And then you're able to make
those decisions to move forward.
Business is no different.
So we're going to be
answering these questions
that you see in column G using
our campaign data worksheet.
We're going to be using this
data throughout most of our time
together this semester
because I want
to give you all the sense of
familiarity with the data.
But that way, you can
also focus on the skills
that you're learning in
a familiar environment.
Your practice problems are
going to bring up new data sets
and different business angles,
so you'll get a wide exposure.
But I want you, as
you're following along
with these videos, to
really focus on the why.
Why am I learning this
particular Excel trick?
Why do I approach
data in this way?
Because that critical
thinking is really what's
going to serve you
well in the future.
So let's dive in.
First and foremost, let's
introduce you to the data
that we're working with.
This is simulated
ad campaign data.
And I downloaded this from
Kaggle, which is an open source
data set website.
And these users had
simulated the data.
So it's going to look very
similar to what you would expect
to see if you're at a company
running marketing campaigns,
and this data comes about.
So when I copied the information
from Kaggle about the data set,
you can see that it's
loaded and, kind of, funny.
It's not what we would
expect it to look.
If you click into our
cell address and Utah--
it's a grid system that makes
finding where other people live
or places of
business really easy.
Excel's the same way.
So if we click on B17,
that's this one cell,
we can see that there's
actually a lot of text.
And this isn't the best
way to be able to see it.
So this is why we may want
to start formatting our Excel
sheets differently.
So first thing I'm
going to do is,
I'm going to find
the column that I
want to format differently.
And I'm going to just--
see how it's turned green now.
I'm going to bring my
cursor over and see
how the icon changes.
Right now, we've got
that double arrow.
This allows me to either
shrink my column, which
is not helpful in this
case, or expand my column.
You can do the same
thing with rows.
I can drag, shorten, whatever.
There's other ways
I can do this with.
Maybe I know for
sure that I want
to change this column to be,
for instance, like maybe--
right now, it's at 88.43.
Maybe I want that to
actually be closer to 50.
Your practice
problems will actually
tell you, change
it to this weight.
It's arbitrary.
So what I did is I'm going
to right click on my column,
and I'm going to come down
to this column width option.
I'm going to click on
that and say, yeah,
I actually want it
to be an exact 50.
And then I want my row
to be more fitting.
I don't want all
this white space
because then I can't see all
the rest of the information.
And so what I'm going
to do is I'm actually
going to come down
and see how my expand
or shrink icon pops back up.
Let me place my cursor.
If I double click on
that, it's actually
going to auto adjust,
which is really nice.
And I can do that.
I'm going to click on row 18.
And I'm going to come clear
down to the very end, which
is row 35.
Now, I'm going to hit my Control
button and double click again.
And now, all of a sudden, I have
each row automatically sized,
which is so nice.
You'll also notice that
there's this button up here.
This is called Wrap Text.
Most of the time, this is how
your data is going to read it.
See how it spills
over our B column.
If you had other data here,
it's going to cut off the words.
And especially when we're
working with text data,
we don't want that.
So I'm going to come
back to B, and I'm
going to come up to my menu.
A lot of your formatting, your
basic Word processing stuff,
it's going to be
in this Home tab.
This is where we're
going to be mostly today.
We'll explore these other
tabs as we continue on
through the semester.
I'm going to come up to
this ABC button, though,
and I'm going to click on that.
And that's going
to wrap my text.
So it's going to respect
the column boundary.
But make it so I can actually
see all of the words.
Well, text data is very helpful.
And this is just
information about the data
that we're going
to be working on.
Some of the other nice
things that we can do
is we can actually
create new worksheets.
Each one of these tabs
is called a Worksheet.
And so as I'm going to get into
answering these questions, what
I want to do is, I want to
leave this data the same way.
I don't want to mess
with this at all.
So what I'm going to do is,
I'm going to come down here
to this plus sign.
And I'm going to
create a new worksheet.
And I'm going to call
this campaigns_new.
And I did that--
I double clicked
on the whole sheet,
and that gives me the
ability to change the name.
And then what I'm
going to do is,
I'm going to control all,
which selects all of my data.
You can also start
in A1 and manually
navigate to the very
end of your table.
And then I'm just going
to hit Control-Copy.
You can also right click
and do copy that way.
And then I'm going
to come over and I'm
going to just
paste it over here.
So now, you'll see
that brand new sheet.
And now, in case I
goof something up,
now it's in a nice, safe,
clean space, where I can always
go back to the original data.
And that helps me feel a
little more confident as I'm
working through things, that I'm
not going to goof something up.
You'll notice, as we're
talking about formatting,
we just covered--
I can't see all of that.
It all just looks
like the same value.
When in reality,
it's very different.
These are the names of
our different campaigns.
So I want you to pause
the video for a second
and try to adjust column B
to see how you would make it,
so you can see the full
name of the campaign.
There's lots of different
ways to do this.
You could right click
and hit column width.
And you might say,
OK, let's try 12.
That's still not great.
Let's come back and try 15.
You can also do the
double-click option
to expand that out to see the
full name of the campaign.
So we've got that.
And I'm going to then
move these question
cells by hitting Control-X,
or right click and hit Cut.
And what that does
is it copies it.
But instead of leaving
a version behind,
it actually will
just move it over.
So I, again, highlighted
what I wanted, Control-X,
and then Control-V paste.
Or you can right click and
use your paste options there.
So we've now gone ahead
and resized column B.
And we've got all these
different rows of information.
Row 1 is what we call a header.
And that contains
our column names.
If you're taking 2100
alongside this class,
you'll be using column names
a lot from data tables.
Same thing in Excel.
This is what gives
us the description
of what each one of these
columns actually means.
If we didn't have these column
names, we could figure it out.
We can say, OK,
column A, column D.
But it's not the most
helpful situation.
So now, let's talk
about data types.
There's lots of
different kinds of data.
We've got text data, which
we've just been working with.
We also have date
data and numeric data.
And numeric data
can be all kinds.
It can be monetary.
It can be sheer number.
Lots of different kinds.
So what we're going to do is
we're going to look up here,
and we're going to see we have
a start date and an end date
column.
And this doesn't look
like a normal date to you.
And in the other version,
the original version,
we had an actual date.
When we copied it over,
it transcribed it to just
be the internal Excel number.
So let's change that
back to date data.
So I'm going to
click on column C.
And I'm going to come up
here to this General button.
Again, we're in this
Home tab, General.
I'm going to click
that drop down.
And then I've got a bunch of
different data type options.
So in this case, I'm
going to hit Short Date.
And then for End Date,
let's do Long Date just
so that way you can
see the difference.
We're going to be working a
lot more with the time data
and formatting it more later.
So we're not going to worry
about that too much right now.
Just know that you can
change the data type up here.
We also have duration in days.
Excel tries its best to
recognize what it is.
So if it's general and you're
starting to use formulas on it,
and it looks like
a number, Excel
is going to treat
it like a number.
But then we also
have total budget,
which is a monetary value.
And so what we can do is, we can
come up to here and we can say,
I actually need this
to be in dollars.
And it automatically changes
up here to accounting.
So if I ever wanted to use
some conditional formatting,
then it'll let me understand.
If it's a positive number,
maybe let's make it green.
If we're actually losing
money, then let's turn it red.
And it'll really help capture
what's going on with your data.
And then you're also making
for sure certain that we're
treating these as dollars.
So let's go ahead and look
at these different questions
that we have.
When you're working in data,
it's not very prescriptive.
In your practice
problems, you're
going to be walked through
step by step by step.
In the real world,
though, you're
going to be given this question.
And there's lots of
different ways to solve it.
And so what we're
going to do is,
we're going to
talk through how we
want to approach each of
these questions, which
are very reasonable questions.
So that first question is, what
is the average daily budget
for each campaign?
So in order to
figure this out, it
sounds like it wants
me to add a column.
I want to know for
campaign 1 launch
all the way down to
campaign 50 summer.
I want to know for how
many days on average,
am I spent-- how
much am I spending?
So I'm going to give this a
new column name in column G,
and I'm going to say
average_daily_budget.
And when we're
averaging something,
we add up every instance and
then divide by how many we have.
So in this case, we already have
both of those numbers calculated
for us.
We have our total
budget, and then we
have how many days
the campaign ran.
And so what I'm going to
do is create a formula.
And in order to create a
formula, what I'm going to do
is, I'm going to
hit the equals sign.
And this tells Excel,
hey, I want you
to start calculating something.
And I'm going to
click or reference
the cell address that I want
Excel to do my calculation for.
So hit my equals sign.
And I'm just going
to click on F2.
And then I'm going to divide
it by E2 because that's
going to say, for
each of your 59 days,
you're spending
about $407, Which
equates to our total budget.
There's another
way we can do that.
We can just directly say, I
want to-- now, I'm in row 3.
I'm going to say, type
in F3 divided by E3.
And you'll notice as
I'm typing these in,
this very nice thing happens,
where you can actually
see which cells
you're referencing,
which is super nice.
And I could, in theory, go
through and manually calculate
each one of these based
off of their cells.
But that's going to
take a long time.
Not so much in this case.
We only have 40--
not 50 rows of data.
But if you have thousands
and thousands of rows,
you're not going to want
to calculate that by hand.
So what I like to do is I
come to the corner of the cell
and see now how my
cursor has turned
into that black crosshair.
If I double click on that,
what it's going to do
is it's going to automatically
pull my formula that I just
created all the way down.
And what I need to do is I want
to click on the very last one
to make sure that my
references still make sense,
that it's pulled it
all the way down.
So now, I know what my
average daily budget
is for each campaign.
And now, what I want to know is,
what is the most expensive ad
campaign?
This is a little bit of
an ambiguous question
because does it
mean my total budget
or my average daily budget?
So I may want to
go in and actually
clarify with whoever asked me
this question, what they mean.
So let's do both.
So first, let's look at
the total budget version.
So what I'm going
to do is, I'm going
to highlight all of my data.
And I can do that.
I can start in A1.
And I have to hit
my Shift button.
And that Shift button
is going to allow
me to highlight everything
between the final cell.
So it'll go as far over--
so in this case, column G--
and as far down as I clicked.
And we're going to do
something called a sort.
And if you come up-- again,
we're in that Home tab still--
you have this editing
button Filter and Sort.
And I'm going to click Filter.
And what that lets
me do is it actually
lets me, say, if I
actually only want
to see campaign
IDs less than 10,
I can just only see those rows.
It automatically hides
all the other data.
This is super helpful
in a lot of cases,
which we'll talk keep talking
about through the semester.
But what it also lets
me do is it lets me.
So if I want to know what the
most expensive ad campaign is
based off of total
budget, I'm going
to come to column F,
which is my total budget.
I'm going to click
on that drop down.
And I'm going to
largest to smallest.
You'll notice that before our
campaign, IDs were in order.
It was one through 50.
But now, we're
showing, hey, actually,
our campaign 20 in the winter
time was the most expensive
that we had, followed
by 46, and then 17.
So what I may want to do is,
I may want to come up here.
And I might just give
it a little highlight.
So I'm going to,
again, hit Shift
and just click the first part
and the last part of my row.
And I'm going to
highlight that to be blue,
just so that way we can keep
track of it as we move around.
Now, I want you
to pause the video
and sort it based off of
the average daily budget.
Which one's the most
expensive based off of that?
So I'm going to
do the same thing.
I'm going to come to
this arrow, and I'm
going to largest to smallest.
You'll notice our
most expensive budget
as far as total budget dollars
actually move down to row 11.
Because even though campaign 38
Q3 didn't spend as much money,
they spent a whole lot of money
in a short amount of time.
And so I can give
that a highlight, too.
So now, I can go
back and say, I've
got two expensive campaigns.
I've got this one, which
is the most expensive
average daily budget,
followed by campaign 20,
which had the biggest
overall total budget.
And that's really
helpful to understand
where is our money
going, and understand
how that changes over time.
Let's do another sort example.
So what is the
shortest ad campaign?
I'm going to have
you pause the video,
and go ahead and try
that on your own.
Great.
So what I would do is, I would
come over to this duration days.
And instead of
largest to smallest,
I'm going to sort
smallest to largest.
And now, I see that campaign
50 in the summertime
was the shortest.
It's just over a
month that it ran.
And then this last
question is kind of tricky.
So I want to know what
percentage of the total campaign
budge I've got?
2025 campaign budgets here.
How much does this
campaign 15 make up?
How much does
campaign 40 make up?
So what we're going to do
is a few different things.
First of all, I'm going to
resort it just to keep it easy.
And I'm going to
add another cell.
I'm going to put this far
away from the rest of my table
because this is a
value that I'm going
to reference over and over.
And so I first want to know how
much I spent in ad campaigns
across this whole year.
So in order to do that, I'm
going to sum this information,
And I'm going to
reference all of that.
And so now, I know this is
the total ad spend up above.
And I want to know
what the percentage is.
So if I were to do
this for just row 1,
I'm going to take my total
budget here and divide it.
And if you remember from high
school or your current math
class, percentages, you got
to move the decimal over.
But Excel has a
really nice button,
where I can just hit
percentage style,
and it'll round it
up and do it for me.
When we did the average
daily budget, what happened?
When we clicked
all the way down,
it moved our references
along with it.
And so in this particular case,
what happens when I try that?
I'm just going to drag it
down a few so we can see.
And let's see what our issue is.
We can do this a couple ways.
We can click in our
formula box up here,
and we can see say, oh,
it moved down with it.
We can also come up to Formulas,
which is this button up here.
And we have this really nice
thing called Formula Auditing.
And what it does is,
you can have it show
the formula, which is nice.
We already did that
when we clicked on it.
But we can trace precedents.
And what that does
is, it actually
points to the cells themselves.
It's not so much a big
deal when we're just
dealing with two cells
like we are right now.
It becomes very, very useful if
you are starting to really get
into embedding if statements,
like if this is over $50,000,
then return a value of 2,
or something like that.
And when our formulas start
to get a lot more complicated,
it becomes really nice to
be able to actively see
where this data is coming from.
So I'm going to
remove our arrows.
Something happened here.
When we start pulling our
formulas down like that,
it's going to automatically
adjust the reference point.
I don't want this K1
value to move at all.
I want each one of our rows
to reference that value.
So what I can do is,
I can put dollar signs
in front of my
column information
and in front of my
row information.
And so now what that does is
the dollar signs say to Excel,
lock this in place.
I don't want you
to move anymore.
And we can double
click throughout
to make sure that's
actually working.
I want you to try to just delete
the dollar sign from the front
of the K and see what happens.
Does anything change?
What happens if I pull it over?
Right now, all of a sudden,
my columns are able to adjust.
What happens if I just have
it in front of my columns,
but not my row?
It's not moving over with it.
If I pull it over 1, I'm still
referencing my locked-in K
column.
But as I move it down, it's
still moving with the rows.
So sometimes it takes a second
to really try to remember.
You can try multiple times
to see if what is happening
makes sense.
So in this particular
case, yes, I just
need the dollar sign in front
of my row for this K1 value.
And you can also have
it show you the formula,
which we can see here.
We can see where
all that comes from.
And we can also
evaluate the formula.
So what this does is it
says, OK, we've got F2.
And I'm going to hit Evaluate.
And you can see how
it subs the value in.
And then I'm going to
hit Evaluate again.
So now, we've got that K1 value
and then how it ends up looking.
And that's really nice
because, again, it shows you,
is this value that you're
returning one that you expected?
And so now, we can come in here.
We can hit Control-A again.
And we can add our
sorting filter.
And so now, we can call
this percent of total.
And now if we sort by
largest to smallest,
now we can say, OK, this
one campaign made up
4% of our totals.
And then if we do
like a running total--
we're just going to do this
plus our current one, which
for the first one isn't
going to do anything.
It's Control-Z because I want
to do the previous value.
So now, I can see
that actually only--
let's come down here--
only seven of my campaigns
make up about 25%
of my overall
campaigns out of 50.
And so that can help
us, again, start
to evaluate are these
campaigns that we're pouring
so much money in worth it?
So that's just really a
taste of the different things
that we're doing this week.
I would recommend going
to your practice problems.
And as a new summary
statistic pops up,
watch the video related to that.
We can count, we
can add, we can--
all of these different things.
Continue to read the textbook
and watch those videos
as you're working through
your practice problems.
And if you have any
questions, remember
there is that Q&A thread on this
week's module that you can--
I'm more than happy to
answer your questions there,
or you're welcome to schedule
a time to meet with me,
or pop into Friday
office hour at noon.
Thanks, and good
luck with Excel.